Okay, so here we're going to discuss risk
response strategies for a positive risk.
In a previous video, we discussed risk
response strategies for a negative risk.
This one is going to be now for a positive
risk or an opportunity.
All right, so the five risk response
strategies and for an opportunity are
escalate, share, enhance, exploit and
accept.
Notice escalate and accept are identical
to what we talked about in a negative risk
or a risk response strategy is for a
negative risk.
For both negative and positive,
you can escalate or accept.
And exactly the same.
Escalate means escalate it to higher
authority.
We don't have the authority to make this
decision to try and get this opportunity
or accept active acceptance or passive
acceptance, exactly the same as before.
So let's talk about the middle three.
Share.
Share basically means sharing with a third
party, sharing with a partnership,
right?
You may come across this term called a
teaming agreement or a joint venture.
A teaming agreement is the same thing as a
joint venture, which is
a temporary partnership.
So as a simple example, then, let's say
we're bidding on a contract.
We may get this contract.
We may not get this contract.
We're bidding on a contract.
If we get it, it's a good thing.
That's why it's an opportunity.
now there's one skill that our
organization is lacking and so we know
then that's going to hinder us from
getting this contract we're bidding on
this contract and there's one skill our
organization doesn't have so we decide
well let's go into a partnership with a
company that specializes in those skills
that we don't have so now the two of us
then are going to bid on this contract and
if we get this contract we
are going to share in that
contract Now, we're going
to share the opportunity.
So a share is always,
there is a third part
involved, there is a
partnership involved in a share.
Enhance, another strategy is enhance,
and enhance is just increasing the
probability, increasing the likelihood or
increasing the probability.
So in the same example then, we're bidding
on this contract.
Instead of finding a partner, let's say we
hired a team of people
that have those skills.
We hire a team of
people that have those skill
sets, so that our organization is lacking.
So now our organization has those skill
sets.
And so now that's going
to increase the likelihood,
increase the probability
of us getting this contract.
It's not guaranteed, but it's increase the
probability.
Now, be very careful with share and
enhance.
In both cases, you've just increased a
probability, right?
Even with a share,
even if we're going to a
temporary partnership,
that's not guaranteed.
Right.
But the only difference, right,
the only thing that makes, or the only
strategy, the only reason
why share would be a correct
answer is because, because
there is a third party involved.
That is the only thing that distinguishes
between a share and an enhance.
In both cases, you've increased a
probability.
But if there's a third party involved,
there's a team and agreement, a temporary
partnership involved, then the strategy
will be a share.
If there is no partnership involved,
the strategy will be enhanced.
So always be careful when you're reading
questions or reading scenarios.
Another strategy then is exploit.
An exploit means taking the advantage of,
right?
You make sure the opportunity occurs.
You take advantage of the opportunity.
I mean, that's what an exploit means,
taking advantage of the situation.
So let's say, in the same example,
in the previous example, our potential
customer came to us,
and they told us, if you
hire a team of people,
we will give you that cost.
contract.
So you just go, you hire a team of people,
and now you've gotten that contract.
That would be an example of an exploit.
Because you've made a decision and your
decision is going to
result in a positive risk.
It will result in that opportunity.
So that would be an exploit.
If you hire a team of people, we will give
you that contract.
So you take advantage of that.
You hire a team of people?
No, you've got that contract.
That would be an example of an exploit.
Another common example of an exploit that
you see is using existing resources,
using existing machines.
So let's say, you know, we need to use a
specialized machine and we have a budget
to procure this machine from a third
party.
But then we're also being told,
we find out that another division,
another department in our
organization has the same
machine or a very similar
machine that we could use.
And it will be available to us at a much
lower cost.
So we're going to take advantage of that.
We're going to exploit the opportunity to
save money on our project by using this
existing machine, by using this existing
resource.
Another strategy then is accept.
And again, two types of acceptance,
active and passive.
Active acceptance means putting aside
money and contingency.
reserves again?
I'd say you might be wondering,
well, hang on.
There's a positive risk.
What do you mean by putting money aside in
contingency reserve?
Well, let's say there's an opportunity
that material prices might come right down.
There's an opportunity that might happen.
Material prices come to a rock bottom
price.
So we want to take advantage of that and
buy tons of raw materials at this,
you know, real low price before the prices
go back up again.
But we don't know if material prices will
come right down or not.
So we might put money in our contingency
reserves just in case.
Now, if we don't have
the authority to make
that decision, then we
would need to escalate.
We don't have the authority, so we
escalate that decision.
There's a strategy then
is passive acceptance,
and again, passive
acceptance is do nothing.
In this case, we'll just figure it out.
For example, if we get this contract
great, we're bidding on this contract,
but we're not going to do anything about
it.
We'll just send in the contract if we get
it great, if we don't, we're not going to
be, you know, we're not going to worry
about it, right?
So that's what the passive acceptance is,
right?
We're not going to deal with it,
We're not going to, you know, just do
nothing.
Okay.
All right, so those are strategies then
for a positive, for a positive risk.
Now, again, just give you a little exam
strategy here, an exam tip.
So you see a question, I see a scenario,
right?
And they're asking, you know, what
response strategy should you be choosing?
Well, remember, risk
response strategies for a
positive risk and a negative
risk are different, right?
The middle three are different.
With a negative risk, avoid, transfer,
mitigate.
With a positive risk, it's share,
enhance, and exploit.
So you always use the right terminology in
the right context.
Now, if it is a positive risk, this is
a third party involved, it's a share.
If it increase the probability,
there's no third party involved,
it's an enhance.
If it's guaranteed that, you
know, this decision you're
making will result in
whatever the opportunity is.
It's absolutely guaranteed.
Then it's an exploit.
Okay.
So again, always kind of like we'll look
out for that.
You use a right terminology in the right
context.
You share a positive risk.
You don't share a negative risk,
right?
You transfer a negative risk, right?
You exploit a positive risk.
You don't exploit a negative risk.
You avoid a negative risk.
You eliminate a negative risk.
So always make sure you use the right
terminology in the right context.